Guide to the David Starr Jordan Papers SC0058
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
David Starr Jordan papers
1861-1964
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Jordan, David Starr
SC0058
250.25 Linear Feet
Provenance
David Starr Jordan, the first president of Stanford University, and Orrin Leslie Elliott, first registrar, used adjacent offices and later shared a common secretary in George A. Clark during the early years of the institution. Under this arrangement their correspondence files were intermixed, and although three separate categories were maintained--President's Office, General Letters, and University Letters--these distinctions were so vague as to prove meaningless. Thus, many hundreds of the letters of the letters in the combined files were requests for catalogs or information about the institution by potential students. All of the incoming letters and loose carbons and drafts of outgoing letters were copied into letterpress books. It is assumed that these papers, official and unofficial, remained in the custody of the University.
When Dr. Jordan retired in 1913, a new file was created for his correspondence as chancellor, and later, chancellor emeritus. The manner of arranging this correspondence is unknown.
In 1919, Dr. Jordan gave the Stanford Library a large amount of manuscript material of which the exact nature has not been determined. Included in this gift were the Papers of the Fur Seal Commission maintained by Dr. Jordan's and the Commission's secretary, George A. Clark. In that same year, Dr. Jordan gave the Hoover Collection (now the Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace) his award-winning Plan of Education for Peace. Further gifts to the Hoover Collection followed in 1925-26, 1926-27, and 1928-29.
Dr. Jordan died in 1931, and in 1933-34, his widow gave the Stanford Main Library manuscripts, journals, poems, and notebooks. In that same year, Mrs. Jordan gave Cornell, Dr. Jordan's alma mater, books and student mementos, and other materials pertaining to Jordan's student days.
In September 1934, the University registrar reported that he had employed an assistant to file the Jordan papers. In reporting to the registrar, the assistant noted that she found so much overlapping that it is impossible to make a clear segregation. I find that Mrs. Jordan was arranging the materials in many miscellaneous packages which must all be arranged by subject. It would be difficult to arrange materials chronologically because dates are lacking... so the alphabetical arrangement is necessary. In addition to arranging the files, the assistant segregated several thousand letters of interest to Dr. Elliott, who at this time was writing a history of the University.
In 1941, the Hoover Library moved into a new multi-story building and assumed the custody of all the Jordan papers except the official files stored in the President's vault. In 1943-44, Mrs. Jordan sent 36 files and three cartons of correspondence, a diary, and other papers to Hoover, making a grand total of 107 boxes. In October, 1945, all the cartons except 24 concerned with peace were returned to the Main Library.
At some unknown date, manuscript record books and some correspondence on fishes was turned over to the Division of Systematic Biology. These have subsequently been delivered to the Archives for inclusion in the Jordan files.
In 1965, the Stanford Board of Trustees established the Stanford University Archives, which absorbed the Stanford Collection, a memorabilia collection long maintained by the Library. At that time, the Stanford Collection contained 84 boxes of Jordan Papers arranged by subject. Most of these papers dated after Dr. Jordan's retirement as President, or were his personal correspondence.
Less than a year after its establishment, the Archives received the Jordan files from the President's Office vault, of which three cartons were hopelessly damaged by mildew. A careful search of accessible campus storage areas brought additional Jordan letters, including those segregated for Dr. Elliott. After the microfilm edition of the Jordan Papers was approved by the NHPRC, 59 volumes of Dr. Jordan's letter books (chronological files) were turned over to the Archives by the Registrar's Office.
Scope and Content Note
The Jordan Papers span 1861-1951, although the bulk of the collection dates between 1891 and 1929. Very few items pre-date Jordan's connection with Stanford University and there is very little material after the severe stroke he suffered in the summer of 1929. The papers of Jessie Knight Jordan [Series I-F], cover the two years of Jordan's illness, her reminiscences and the memoires of his old friends.
The collection consists primarily of Jordan's voluminous correspondence (62.25 linear ft.) relating to professional and university matters, but also contains other types of material such as writings (published and unpublished), clippings, journals and diaries, scrapbooks, financial papers, biographical and genealogical information, and photographs.
The major subjects are those which deeply involved David Starr Jordan during his lifetime. In his autobiography, The Days of a Man, he described himself as A Naturalist, Teacher, and Minor Prophet of Democracy.
Jordan was a naturalist-first a botanist and secondly and of greater significance an ichthyologist. In the latter field, his works are still considered authoritative. In this role he was also interested in conservation, zoological nomenclature and the protection of fur seals, which endeavor was extremely important and highly documented.
All his life he was a teacher. Even when he was a university president at Indiana and Stanford he personally taught courses. His career as a public lecturer, beginning in 1871, was an educational endeavor-to teach natural history, moral goals and standards, the progress of education and peace and international arbitration.
As an educator Jordan brought the separation of education from religion and the system of elective courses learned at Cornell to the new western universities. In the field of science he emphasized the importance of field and laboratory work rather than mere reliance on textbooks. He developed the idea of a junior college and was responsible for developing Stanford University into an intellectually competitive university rather than the technical training school envisioned by the founders.
Social Darwinism was the major cause of Jordan's devotion to peace and his interests in eugenics, temperance, non-smoking and genealogy. Anything that, to his mind, threatened to weaken or destroy man's natural abilities and health, Jordan fought against. According to Jordan, was affected the degeneration of the race by destroying the most promising men and leaving the least desirable at home to reproduce and create the future generations. He was limited by his puritan heritage and his belief in the superiority of a biological, intellectual elite.
The David Starr Jordan Papers in the Hoover Institution Archives contain the majority of Jordan's papers relating to politics and pacifism. A guide to that collection is available in the reading room of the Department of Special Collections.
Biographical Sketch
David Starr Jordan was born at Gainesville, New York, on January 19, 1851. His father was a farmer of comfortable circumstances who cared a great deal more for poets than for the current agricultural literature. Young Jordan developed a marked distate for the routine labors of the farm, preferring to collect butterflies and flowers to hauling hay. Jordan's schooling provided more freedom than was common for boys of his generation and offered him the opportunity to catalogue the plants of his native country in addition to learning French, Latin, history, and poetry.
In March, 1869, Jordan won a competitive examination for a scholarship from Wyoming County and entered Cornell University to join the first freshman class (which had begun work in the fall of 1868). His progress was such that he was appointed an instructor in botany in his junior year. Upon presentation of his thesis Wild Flowers of Wyoming County, Jordan received the M.S. degree from Cornell in 1872. Thus, in less than four years, Jordan received the master's degree upon completion of an undergraduate course.
After graduation, Jordan became professor of natural history at Lombard University, Galesburg, Illinois, 1872-73, spent the summer of 1873 at Penikese Island with naturalist Louis Agassiz, served as principal of the Collegiate Institute in Appleton, Wisconsin, 1873-74, and was a teacher at the Indianapolis High School in 1874-75.
In March, 1875, Jordan married Susan Bowen. Mrs. Jordan died in 1885, and in 1887, Jordan married Jessie Louise Knight. Jessie Knight Jordan played an important role in Jordan's life, especially during his last years when illnes incapacitated him. Since she conducted his business for him and carried on with some of his causes after he died, the papers of Mrs. Jordan are included in this collection.
In 1875, Jordan received his M.D. from Indiana Medical College and that same year, became professor of biology at Butler University. According to Jordan, the medical degree was obtained with no intention of going into medical practice, but with a view toward better teaching of Biology. In 1878, he received his Ph.D. from Butler. In 1879, Dr. Jordan moved to Indiana University as professor of natural history, and in January, 1885, he became president of Indiana University.
During these early years, Jordan concentrated more and more on fishes, due to the influential experience at Penikese with Louis Agassiz. He spent his summers, often at his own expense, collecting data for the U.S. Fish Commission, later Bureau of Fish and Fisheries, or the U.S. Census Bureau. In the course of his long career he studied and catalogued fish of the rivers of the United States and Alaska; Pacific Coast salmon, fish of Japan, Sinaloa, Mexico, Samoa, and Hawaii. He also served on numerous commissions, including the joint commission investigating the Bering Sea fur seal.
In the summer of 1881, Dr. Jordan climbed the Matterhorn, and for years thereafter, one of his most popular lectures to general audiences was his description of this exciting event. As a lecturer, Jordan's services were constantly in demand. In addition to his Matterhorn talk, he often spoke about evolution, education, and to youth groups on morality, temperance, and physical well-being.
In the Spring of 1891, Leland Stanford offered Jordan the presidency of the university established in memory of the Senator's late son. Dr. Jordan accepted and in March began to recruit a faculty for the soon-to-open institution. Dr. Jordan's first choice was John Casper Branner, who became Stanford's second president. While in Boston, Dr. Jordan wrote Dr. Branner that he was discouraged about recruiting in New England, where there are men who nothing would induce to go west of Springfield, and men whose regret of their lives is that they were born outside of Boston. Nonetheless, a faculty was recruited--in large measure from Cornell and Indiana--and school commenced October 1, 1891.
Mr. Stanford died in June, 1893, and Stanford University faced an uncertain future. A long probate period and a suit by the federal government for funds advanced to build the Central Pacific Railroad tempered the growth of the University until 1899. During this period, Dr. Jordan stood by Mrs. Stanford, who expended great energy and the restricted resources available to her to keep the University open. During what he called the six pretty long years, Jordan continued his ichthyological work and found time to be president of the California Academy of Sciences (1896-1904 and 1908-1912). In 1892, he helped found the Sierra Club and, henceforth, took personal interest in various efforts to preserve selected stands of redwood trees as parks. He was aslo active in the establishment of Mr. Rainier and Yosemite as national parks, and in conservation movements generally.
In 1899, when the University received its inheritance and legal actions against the estate were a thing of the past, Mrs. Stanford began a six-year building program to complete the physical structure of the University. To Jordan, the stone age was another impediment to improving the scholastic position of Stanford.
Having achieved fame as an ichthyologist and educator, Jordan turned his interest to international peace, that was to occupy much of his later life. The Spanish-American War and the Boer War in Africa provided the vehicles to express his concern. In 1910 he became the chief director of the World Peace Foundation, endowed by Edwin Ginn, and president of the International School of Peace. Events in Europe led Jordan to request extended leaves from the University in order to lecture on the follies of war. In 1913 he resigned as president, became chancellor of the University, and devoted full time to the cause of peace.
During his later years as president of Stanford and in addition to his devotion to the peace cause, Jordan found time to serve as a member of the International Committee on Zoological Nomenclature (1904), president of the American Association for the Advancement of Science (1909-1910), vice-president of the International Congress of Zoologists (1910), and to receive honorary degrees from Johns Hopkins University (1902), Illinois College (1905), and Indiana University (1909).
During his retirement Jordan continued his travels in the interest of classifying fish and was awarded the Order of the Rising Sun by Japan for his scientific work (1922). His continuing efforts on behalf of peace brought him the Herman Peace Prize in 1924, and his last public address on July 30, 1928, was titled No More War. Jordan died on September 19, 1931, after an illness of several years.
Provenance
Personal papers given by Mrs. David Starr Jordan and others; official papers transferred from the Stanford University President's Office.
Access Restrictions
The materials are open for research use.
San Francisco Earthquake and Fire, Calif., 1906; Hearst, Phoebe Apperson.; Carnegie, Andrew, 1835-1919; Harper, William Rainey,; Elder, Paul.; Fels, Joseph.; Dole, Nathan Haskell.; Doyle, John T. (John Thomas), 1819-1906; Dreiser, Theodore.; DuBois, William Edward Burghardt.; Bierce, Ambrose, 1842-1914?; Frémont, Jessie Benton, 1824-1902; Otis, Harrison Gray; Cubberley, Ellwood Patterson; Lummis, Charles Fletcher; Harrison, Benjamin; Hearst, William Randolph, 1863-1951; Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924; Wilbur, Ray L. (Ray Lyman); Hughes, Charles Evans, 1962-1948; Burbank, Luther, 1849-1926; Evermann, Barton Warren, 1853-1932; Voorhees, Daniel Wolsey.; Veblen, Thorstein (Thorstein Bunde); Jordan, David Starr; Voorsanger, Jacob.; White, Andrew Dickson,; Hopkins, Timothy; Camp, Walter Chauncey; Sutro, Adolph.; Stoddard, Charles Warren.; Sinclair, Upton; Taft, William H. (William Howard), 1857-1930; Swain, Joseph.; Stanford University -- General subdivision--Students.;; Turner, Frederick Jackson.; Taylor, Edward Robeson.; Sanger, Margaret Higgins.; Stanford, Jane Lathrop; Ross, Edward Alsworth, 1866-1951; White, Stephen Mallory; Royce, Josiah.; Roosevelt, Theodore.; Anderson, Melville Best; Root, Elihu, 1845-1937; Barnes, Earl; Reid, Whitelaw.; Branner, John Casper, 1850-1922; Barnes, Mary Sheldon; Jordan, Jessie Knight; Rolph, James, Jr.; Phelan, James Duval.; Pinchot, Gifford.; Pardee, George C.; Campbell, Douglas Houghton; Olivetti, Camillo.; Olney, Warren.; Norris, Charles Gilman.; Wheeler, Benjamin Ide; Older, Fremont.; Hoover, Herbert; Muir, John.; Mills, Sarah Lincoln.; Markham, Edwin.; McKinley, William, 1843-1901; MacDowell, Edward Alexander.; McClure, Samuel Sidney.; Loeb, Jacques.; Field, Charles K. (Charles Kellogg), 1873-1948; Lodge, Henry Cabot.; Dudley, William Russel, 1849-1911; LeConte, Joseph.; Lea, Homer.; Kellogg, Vernon Lyman.; Bryan, William Jennings; Crocker, Charles Frederick.; Huntington, Collis Potter.; Irwin, Will, 1873-1948; Cleveland, Stephen Grover.; Coolbrith, Ina Donna.; Coolidge, Dane.; Cooper, Sarah B.; Jordan, David Starr; Anthony, Susan B. (Susan Brownell), 1820-1906; Washington, Booker T.; Adams, Bristow, 1875-1957; Burgess, Frank Gelett.; Stanford, Thomas Welton; Addams, Jane.; Agassiz, Alexander.; Bell, Alexander Graham.; Hoover, Lou Henry, 1874-1944; Davis, Horace.; Dayal, Har.; Bliven, Bruce.; de Young, Meichel Harry.; Dole, Charles Fletcher.; James, William; Dewey, John.; Muybridge, Eadweard, 1830-1904; Dewey, Melvil.
- Correspondence, Series I
  - General Correspondence, 1872-1931; Series I-A
    Scope and Content
    Mostly, but not exclusively, incoming correspondence through 1910 when letter books were discontinued. Then, incoming and copies of outgoing letters in chronological order and within each day alphabetically by sender. Much of the early correspondence which pertains to routine university affairs was transferred to Series IB. Some examples were retained to indicate the activities and problems of a new president of a new private university with living founders. Where enclosures were found, these were kept with the covering letter.
    Undated items appear at the end of the month or year where these can be determined or at the end of the sub-series. An addenda of dated items discovered or added to the collection after the initial processing appears at the very end of the sub-series.
    There is also a special file of earthquake letters following April, 1906.
    [A card file name index, separately maintained in the Reading Room, will give quick access to correspondence of individuals or organizations.]
    - 1872-1879 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1880-1885 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1886-1889 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1890 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1891, January-April (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1891, May 1-10 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1891, May 11-20 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1891, May 21-31 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 1891, June 1-15 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 1891, June 16-30 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Pre-April 1891, G-H (Box 1a, Folder a)
    - Pre-April 1891, I-R (Box 1a, Folder b)
    - Pre-April 1891, S-Z (Box 1a, Folder c)
    - 1891, July 1-9 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - 1891, July 10-29 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - 1891, August (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - 1891, September (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - 1891, October 1-15 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - 1891, Oct 16-30, and undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - 1891, November 1-15 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - 1891, November 16-30 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - 1891, December 1-15 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - 1891, December 16-31 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - 1892, January 1-15 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - 1892, January 16-31 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - 1892, February 1-10 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - 1892, February 11-29 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - 1892, March-July (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - 1892, August-September (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - 1892, October (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - 1892, November (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - 1892, December (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - 1893, January (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - 1893, February 1-14 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - 1893, February 15-28 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - 1893, March 1-15 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - 1893, March 16-31 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - 1893 April 1-15 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - 1893, April 16-30 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - 1893, May 1-15 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - 1893, May 16-31 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - 1893, June 1-10 (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - 1893, June 12-30 (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - 1893, July 1-15 (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - 1893, July 16-30 (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - 1893, August 1-15 (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - 1893, August 16-31 (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - 1893, September 1-15 (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - 1893, September 16-30 (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - 1893, October 1-15 (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - 1893, October 16-31 (Box 5, Folder 48)
    - 1893, November 1-15 (Box 6, Folder 49)
    - 1893, Nov 16-30, and undated (Box 6, Folder 50)
    - 1893, December 1-15 (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - 1893, Dec 16-31, and undated (Box 6, Folder 52)
    - 1894, January 1-10 (Box 6, Folder 53)
    - 1894, January 11-20 (Box 6, Folder 54)
    - 1894, Jan 21-31, and undated (Box 6, Folder 55)
    - 1894, February 1-14 (Box 6, Folder 56)
    - 1894, Feb 15-28, and undated (Box 6, Folder 57)
    - 1894, March 1-15 (Box 7, Folder 58)
    - 1894, Mar 16-31, and undated (Box 7, Folder 59)
    - 1894, April 1-15 (Box 7, Folder 60)
    - 1894, Apr 16-30, and undated (Box 7, Folder 61)
    - 1894, May 1-15 (Box 7, Folder 62)
    - 1894, May 15-31 (Box 7, Folder 63)
    - 1894, June 1-30 (Box 7, Folder 64)
    - 1894, July 1-31 (Box 7, Folder 65)
    - 1894, August 1-15 (Box 7, Folder 66)
    - 1894, Aug 15-31, and undated (Box 7, Folder 67)
    - 1894, September 1-20 (Box 8, Folder 68)
    - 1894, Sep ember 20-31, and undated (Box 8, Folder 69)
    - 1894, October 1-10 (Box 8, Folder 70)
    - 1894, October 11-20 (Box 8, Folder 71)
    - 1894, Oct 21-31, and undated (Box 8, Folder 72)
    - 1894, November 1-10 (Box 8, Folder 73)
    - 1894, November 11-20 (Box 8, Folder 74)
    - 1894, Nov 21-30, and undated (Box 8, Folder 75)
    - 1894, December 1-10 (Box 8, Folder 76)
    - 1894, December 11-20 (Box 8, Folder 77)
    - 1894, Dec 21-31, and undated (Box 8, Folder 78)
    - 1895, January 1-15 (Box 9, Folder 79)
    - 1895, Jan 16-31, and undated (Box 9, Folder 80)
    - 1895, February 1-15 (Box 9, Folder 81)
    - 1895, February 16-28 (Box 9, Folder 82)
    - 1895, March 1-15 (Box 9, Folder 83)
    - 1895, Mar 16-31, and undated (Box 9, Folder 84)
    - 1895, April 1-10 (Box 9, Folder 85)
    - 1895, April 11-20 (Box 9, Folder 86)
    - 1895, Apr 21-30, and undated (Box 9, Folder 87)
    - 1895, May 1-10 (Box 10, Folder 88)
    - 1895, May 11-20 (Box 10, Folder 89)
    - 1895, May 21-31, and undated (Box 10, Folder 90)
    - 1895, June 1-15 (Box 10, Folder 91)
    - 1895, Jun 16-30, and undated (Box 10, Folder 92)
    - 1895, July 1-15 (Box 10, Folder 93)
    - 1895, Jul 16-31, and undated (Box 10, Folder 94)
    - 1895, August 1-15 (Box 10, Folder 95)
    - 1895, Aug 15-31, and undated (Box 10, Folder 96)
    - 1895, September 1-15 (Box 11, Folder 97)
    - 1895, Sep ember 16-31, and undated (Box 11, Folder 98)
    - 1895, October 1-15 (Box 11, Folder 99)
    - 1895, October 16-31 (Box 11, Folder 100)
    - 1895, November 1-15 (Box 11, Folder 101)
    - 1895, Nov 15-30, and undated (Box 11, Folder 102)
    - 1895, December 1-15 (Box 11, Folder 103)
    - 1895, Dec 16-31, and undated (Box 11, Folder 104)
    - 1895, undated (Box 11, Folder 105)
    - 1896, January 1-10 (Box 12, Folder 106)
    - 1896, January 11-20 (Box 12, Folder 107)
    - 1896, Jan 21-31, and undated (Box 12, Folder 108)
    - 1896, February 1-10 (Box 12, Folder 109)
    - 1896, February 11-20 (Box 12, Folder 110)
    - 1896, Feb 21-29, and undated (Box 12, Folder 111)
    - 1896, March 1-5 (Box 12, Folder 112)
    - 1896, March 6-15 (Box 12, Folder 113)
    - 1896, Mar 16-31, and undated (Box 12, Folder 114)
    - 1896, April 1-15 (Box 13, Folder 115)
    - 1896, Apr 16-30, and undated (Box 13, Folder 116)
    - 1896, May 1-15 (Box 13, Folder 117)
    - 1896, May 16-31, and undated (Box 13, Folder 118)
    - 1896, Jun 1-30, and undated (Box 13, Folder 119)
    - 1896, July (Box 13, Folder 120)
    - 1896, August (Box 13, Folder 121)
    - 1896, September (Box 13, Folder 122)
    - 1896, October 1-15 (Box 13, Folder 123)
    - 1896, Oct 16-31, and undated (Box 13, Folder 124)
    - 1896, November 1-15 (Box 13, Folder 125)
    - 1896, Nov 16-31, and undated (Box 13, Folder 126)
    - 1896, December 1-15 (Box 13, Folder 127)
    - 1896, December 16-31 (Box 13, Folder 128)
    - 1896, undated (Box 13, Folder 129)
    - 1897, January 1-10 (Box 14, Folder 130)
    - 1897, January 11-15 (Box 14, Folder 131)
    - 1897, January 16-20 (Box 14, Folder 132)
    - 1897, January 21-25 (Box 14, Folder 133)